Guide to the Samuel Bowles Papers
Yale University Library
Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Bowles papers
1852-1893
MS 94
Bowles, Samuel, 1826-1878.
1 linear foot
The papers include correspondence, legal documents, petitions, pamphlets, and printed material of Samuel Bowles, journalist and political activist. As editor of the influential Springfield Republican, Bowles was a prominent national voice on many public issues during the mid-nineteenth century and included in the papers is correspondence from a number of national political and business figures.
Manuscripts and Archives Sterling Memorial Library 128 Wall Street P.O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520 Web: http://www.library.yale.edu/mssa/ Email: mssa.assist@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-1735 Fax: (203) 432-7441
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Richard Hooker, 1963. Richard Hooker donated his own papers in 1964 and the two were combined as the Bowles-Hooker Collection. This was separated into the Samuel Bowles Papers and the Richard Hooker Papers in 1979.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical History
Samuel Bowles was born in Springfield, Massachusetts, on February 9, 1826. He was the editor of the daily edition of the Springfield Republican from 1844 to 1878. Noted for his willingness to comment on matters of political corruption, he was the subject of a libel suit. Bowles was involved in the Liberal Republican movement of 1872 and worked for the presidential nomination of Charles Francis Adams at the party's convention. He authored several books and was considered a pioneer of independent journalism. Samuel Bowles died in Springfield, Massachusetts, on January 16, 1878.
Description of the Papers
Samuel Bowles II was the second editor of the Springfield Republican, an independent provincial newspaper founded by his father on September 8, 1824. Bowles went to work on the Republican at the age of seventeen, and within a year, he was responsible for changing the paper from a weekly to a daily paper on March 27, 1844. At the Know-Nothing Convention in Philadelphia, 1855, Samuel Bowles gained national fame for himself and his newspaper.
The Samuel Bowles Papers cover the time span 1853-1890; excluding the Civil War period. During the Civil War, the paper doubled its number of subscribers, and its price went from two cents to four cents.
The period 1868-1878, is the richest, providing vivid and detailed accounts of national political and legal issues.
Bowles never hesitated in speaking out on issues of corruption or moral wrong. The famous New York Jail episode of 1868 ensured from his stand against financial swindlers. James Fisk (1834-1872) of New York issued a libel suit for $50,000 against Samuel Bowles who was seized by order of Judge McCunn and jailed in New York for one night.
Another and more famous incident described in the papers is Bowles' denunciation of James Fisk and Jay Gould (1836-1892) as thieves of the stockholders of the Eire Railroad. In this case, Bowles collided with the renowned David Dudley Field (1805-1894) who according to Bowles, could not honorably defend such clients as Fisk and Gould. The published correspondence and letters congratulating Bowles on his stand on the moral issue of the rights and duties of counsel are in this collection.
Bowles' steadfast convictions are best shown in the Liberal Republican movement of 1872. Ample correspondence from Carl Schurz (1829-1906) and some from Horace White (1834-1916) shows the movement in its formation and end. Bowles worked long hours for the presidential nomination of Charles Francis Adams (1807-1886) at this convention; yet he supported Horace Greeley (1811-1872) who was nominated. Information on the Liberal Republican movement of 1872 may be found in the 1872 and 1876 files of the collection.
The Bowles Papers are rich in correspondence from eminent personages of the 1860s and 1870s. Henry Laurens Dawes (1816-1903), James Gillespie Blaine (1830-1893), Nathaniel Prentiss Banks (1825-1894), and Newton Booth (1825-1892) all have large numbers of letters in the collection.
Henry Laurens Dawes, a representative and senator from Massachusetts, was responsible for the Dawes Act of 1887. This act allows individual Indians to own land within reservations and gives citizenship to competent Indians. Dawes helped build a method of Indian education and put Indians under federal criminal law protection. The warm political and personal friendship of Bowles and Dawes is apparent in the many letters containing abundant political agreement as well as exchange of ideas.
The James Gillespie Blaine correspondence is at quite an opposite pole from the Dawes relationship. In 1869, Blaine and Dawes were opponents for the position of Speaker of the United States House of Representatives. Dawes was defeated by Blaine in a contest which Bowles believed Blaine to have won through a coalition with the notorious Benjamin Franklin Butler (1818-1893). An exchange of letters over this issue between Bowles and Blaine forms an interesting part of this collection.
Samuel Bowles did not allow family ties to stand in his way. In 1874, he opposed his brother-in-law, Henry Alexander, Jr., for Congress, because he believed that Alexander's health was not strong enough for the strain. Alexander and Bowles were never reunited. Bowles fired his younger brother, Benjamin Franklin Bowles, from the Republican counting room due to inadequacy for the job. Benjamin died in 1876 in Paris.
Samuel Bowles II is a great figure in the history of American journalism, whose political influence and favor were coveted and feared by the leading thinkers of America during the 1860s and 1870s. He pushed the Springfield Republican, a provincial Massachusetts newspaper, to national prominence, thus establishing a precedent in journalism. A glance at the following list of Bowles' correspondents shows the value of the collection to the history of the United States in the nineteenth century.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, 1853-(1871-1877)-1893, n.d., Series I
  The series is arranged chronologically. Researchers should consult the "Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts" at the end of the finding aid, which provides an item level description of each letter in this series.
  - 1853-1855 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1856-1858 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1860-1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1868-1869 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1870 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1871
    - Jan (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Feb (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Mar-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1872
    - Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - May (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1873
    - Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1874
    - Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Mar-Jul (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1875
    - Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1876
    - Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - May-Aug (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1877
    - Jan-May (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Jun-Aug (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Sep-Dec (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1878, 1890, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Undated, A-N (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Undated, O-Z (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Printed Material and Memorabilia, 1852-1886, n.d., Series II
  - Printed copies of letters regarding the Boston and Chicago Gold Mining Company of Colorado, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pamphlets and clippings regarding Bowles-David Dudley Field controversy, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Clippings on the mayoralty contest in Springfield, Massachusetts, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Willis Phelps vs. Samuel Bowles and others. Defendant's Answer" (3 copies), 1874 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Travelers Record, Vol. XIII, no. 10, 1878 Jan (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Legal documents, 1852, 1855, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Printed request for honorary dinner for Bowles (3 copies), 1868 Dec (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Memorial memorabilia, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Memorabilia, 1857-1883, no date (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Miscellaneous printed material, Pre-1878, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts
  The "Descriptive Catalogue of Manuscripts" consists of an item level description of all letters in the collection. The correspondence itself is located in boxes 1 and 2 in Series I. Researchers can use this index to find relevant materials and then can use the inventory in Series I to determine the specific box that holds the materials.
  - Correspondence
    - Brooks Adams writes Bowles that an audience did not go well at Troy and says that he would like to see Bowles., 1876 Oct 19
    - Brooks Adams gives a severe indictment of Hayes; he suggests he should be deposed., 1877 Feb 24
    - Charles Francis Adams thanks Bowles for a kindness paid him in the Republican. He does not consider himself a public figure., 1875 Jan 13
    - Charles Francis Adams had gone to N.Y. to see his father off on a trip. He discusses a letter written by his father about Wells which was printed in the Republican. He says Bowles has a sure thing., 1872 Apr 26
    - Charles Francis Adams writes again to correct his statement of his father's that he did not think Wells would relish his letter. Adams is much interested in the game between Wells and his father. He believes that is will help the Cincinnati convention., 1872 Apr 27
    - Charles Francis Adams tells Bowles that he made a good fight for his father. Even though he was defeated, he said that Greeley had not been calculated., 1872 May 4
    - Charles Francis Adams, Jr.,cannotagree with Bowles on an unstated point. He says he wishes he could. He writes Bowles to show him different logic., 1873 Feb 26
    - Adams acknowledges a note received from Bowles at Quincy. He points out that railroads do not have clerical force in the commissions and that press abstracts are made by the railroads' own reporters., 1875 Nov 8
    - Charles Francis Adams, Jr., rebukes Bowles for his columns on railroads., 1876 Jan 19
    - Charles Francis Adams, Jr., writes Bowles that he is going to Kansas City and wonders if Bowles will meet him at the train going through Springfield., 1876 Mar 20
    - Charles Francis Adams, Jr., requests a talk with Bowles., 1876 Sep 13
    - Charles Francis Adams, Jr., discusses the Tweed Ring and considers it deplorable that it was attempted to connect Tilden., 1876 Sep 22
    - Charles Francis Adams. Jr., discusses briefly the railroad commissioners in Massachusetts, and mentions some problems he cannot at present discuss with Bowles., 1877 Jan 23
    - Henry Adams requests Bowles to help a friend find a paper mill, despite Adams being for Tilden in the presidential election., 1876 Oct 10
    - Amelia P. Alexander writes Bowles that she is pleased with the result of an election of her brother, Henry, but they are hurt beyond repair over articles published in the Republican., n.y. Nov 4
    - Henry Alexander Jr. encloses a bill for taxes paid for Bowles. He says that his health is bad. Alexander says that if the joint ownership of land is to continue, it must be let to someone. He says that he would prefer merely dividing the property. He states that the disagreementbetween themis not the cause for this., 1875 Apr 3
    - Allen discusses the political influence of the Republican., 1875 Oct 7
    - Charles Allen reports to Bowles that he does not know of the changes proposed in the judicial system., 1877 Jan 3
    - Mary Clemmer Ames thanks Bowles for the generous notice of the novel, Victoire, in the Republican. She laments also her brother and husband in the war and curses the Rebels., 1864 Aug 16
    - Mary Clemmer Ames speaks to Bowles of her poem which appeared in the Republican. She says that it is not to be confused with the partisan orations at Woodstock. She speaks of Blaine as being utterly selfish., 1877 Jul 4
    - Four fragments of letters from Mary Clemmer Ames, no date
    - Banks is going to write Lincoln on the subject of Warren's appointment. He will transmit a letter from Sam G. Ward in favor of a Mr. Hooper with his own approval. He compliments the Republican on being an excellent paper., 1856 Jan 23
    - Banks thanks Bowles for articles relating to the business of the legislature., 1856 Mar 21
    - Banks agrees with the political position of the He discusses Boutwell as one fully possessed of his views., 1856 May 14
    - Banks tells Bowles that he will be happy to talk with him about the "popularsovereigntydogma." He thinks it is fine for Kansas but not for Utah., 1856 Sep 11
    - Banks speaks of Gov. Chase as the guest of honor at an enthusiastic reception and Jefferson Davis as being impudent., 1856 Nov 25
    - Banks proposes a trip to the West with Sam., [1856?]
    - Banks expresses pleasure that Wentworth and Cushing will give just and hearty support to honest measures. He describes Lincoln as being happy., 1858 Jun 19
    - Banks merely states that he is pessimistic as all men are now., 1861 Feb 20
    - Banks is sorry that Bowles has sciatica and that they cannot journey to Europe together. After having read the Inaugural, he fears that Virginia will secede., 1861 Mar 5
    - Banks encloses a note from a Mr. Briggs discussing a "mystery.", n.y. Apr 28
    - Banks says that the California delegation will be first for Seward., n.y. May 7
    - Benjamin Fordyce Barker sends a check to Bowles for copies of the Republican with pleasure. He says that he reads the more than any other paper., 1877 Jan 15
    - Francis Channing Barlow speaks of an agreement with Bowles and a congratulations for his treatment of Field., 1871 Jan 27
    - Agnes Bartlett thanks Bowles for his friendship to her husband who is now dead., 1877 Jan 16
    - W. F. Bartlett writes Bowles that he has read that Dawes stumped Butler's district for him. He hopes that Dawes will not get Sumner's senate seat., 1874 Oct 30
    - Frank Bartlett had been asked to make an address at Lexington of the same sort as his Harvard speech. He fears, however, that he cannot say much on the subject of the North and South without offending his host., 1875 Apr 8
    - Bartlett writes Bowles that he is glad to support a candidate like Adams., 1875 Sep 23
    - W. F. Bartlett sends Bowles a copy of a speech which he made at Haverhill for the opening of a new public library., 1875 Nov 12
    - Bartlett said he did not know of the conference until too late to let Bowles know anything, but he trusts that they will not select such a man as Blaine., 1876 May 5
    - William E. Barton writes to Waldo S. Cook, Republican editor, a letter discussing Josiah G. Holland as the writer of a Republican editorial, Nov. 21, 1863, on the Gettysburg Address. A letter from Cook to Richard Hooker suggests that the above listed letter should be kept in the Republican collection., 1926 Jul 17
    - A. W. Beard wishes to discuss some matters of state policy with Bowles when he comes to Boston., 1875 Nov 4
    - Beard is pleased with a letter which he received from Bowles. He tells Bowles he has been in agreement with the Republican on state matters., 1875 Nov 9
    - Henry Ward Beecher tells Bowles his reasons for not seeing him., 1874 Mar 6
    - Annie Kennedy Bidwell writes Bowles that she is sending him a copy of the Sacramento Record Union, especially thanking him for the interest taken in their Independent Movement., 1875 Sep 9
    - Anna Bigelow wants to know if Bowles approves of an article in the Apr 27 Republican entitled "Mr. Moody's Work in Boston., 1877 May 9
    - John Bigelow gives Bowles his opinion on the state of politics at this time. The opinion comes as a result of Bowles' suggestion for New York hearing Charles Francis Adams., 1875 Oct 7
    - John Bigelow questions what is the matter with the Republican and wonders for what vagaries Bowles is holding Tilden responsible., 1876 May 16
    - Billings expresses sorrow at the death of Bowles' mother., 1871 Jun 6
    - Billings tells of a change in plans for July., 1874 Mar 5
    - Billings has had an attack, and the letter is a discussion of his illness., 1874 Jul 4
    - Billings thanks Bowles for his kind letter and discussed his family., 1874 Jul 15
    - Billings tells Bowles that he has been under the weather a few days, but he wants to thank Bowles for a compliment., 1875 Oct 11
    - Billings congratulates Bowles on a victory. He says that it is bad for Phelps but that Endicott thoroughly sustained Bowles. He says that absolute justice was not nearly done., no date
    - Billings tells Bowles of sleeping sitting up with his feet in warm water., no date
    - Billings tells of his health. He has had some good days. He speaks of Dawes as almost doing too much., n.y., n.m., 20
    - F.W. Bird writes Bowles a congratulatory letter on his trial., 1875 May 8
    - F.W. Bird has a certain testimonial up to $5,000 and is trying to get to $5,000 net., ny, Dec 5
    - Blaine requests copies of articles printed in the Republican on his conduct in the House Speakership Contest. The articles indicated that Blaine was censored by H. L. Dawes for his conduct. Blaine expresses surprise., 1869 Mar 20
    - Blaine accosts Bowles for not naming fact in the offense of Bowles' "fastidious notions." He disavows all that Bowles claimed in the Republican., 1869 Mar 24
    - Blaine states that his reply to Bowles was merely a response to a former Bowles letter and to the erroneous statements in the Republican. Blaine cannot justify what he considers an assault on his character., 1869 Apr 7
    - Blaine asks for the return of his letter and says that he will return Bowles'. He merely repeats that he did not break political ethics and neither did Dawes. He hopes they will be friends., 1869 Apr10
    - Blaine requests Bowles to dine with him., [1869]
    - Blaine sends information on the House Committee to Bowles as a favor for Republican publication., 1873 Dec 30
    - Blaine says that some editor of the Republican is pointing out all of the bad points of the 1875 Maine campaign. Blaine speaks of bitter remarks made in the about him and Lot M. Morrill. (Blaine was appointed to fill the vacancy caused by the resignation of Morrill and took his seat Dec. 4, 1876.), 1875 Aug 11
    - Blaine asks Bowles not to become adamant about one of his letters published in the Boston Journal until he had completely looked the matter over. He says that Henry Wilson's temperament was bad. (Wilson died Nov. 22, 1875.), 1875 Nov 27
    - Blaine gives Bowles a scathing opinion of Charles Francis Adams and the entire Adams family and asks Bowles to print it., 1876 Jan 22
    - George Bliss, attorney for the southern district of New York, begins his letter to Bowles with an article pasted on a letter concerning the blunders at the district attorney's office on the prosecution of Woodhull and Claflin's Weekly. He is very critical of the writers of the Republican and he considers the article an example of Republican criticism. He says that he is not a critic of the Republican but he does not want to be misused by a man who claims to be his friend., 1873 Jul 1
    - Booth wonders if his decisions concerning railroads will make him unpopular and unlikely to be re-elected., 1873 Jul 13
    - He agrees with Bowles' advice to go slow on the railroads, as they do not want them in the hands of the government, which would then be a monarchy in everything but name., 1873 Sep 21
    - Booth discusses thepossibilityof his being elected a U.S. senator., 1874 Jan 1
    - Booth denies talk of his resignation as governor. He says that he has a good legislature and is making progress on the railroads., 1874 Feb 16
    - The railroad people have beaten Booth in the Senate. Booth feels that the Independent Movement in Oregon will work. He feels that Grant has held more trumps than any man living., 1874 Apr 18
    - Booth discusses a fishing trip with Bowles., 1874 Jun 22
    - Booth discusses California politics, especially the politician, Jones., 1875 Feb 3
    - Booth says that the Army Appropriations Bill is before Congress. A controversy exists over the Hayes' cabinet. He thanks Bowles for a sketch of him on his vocabulary., 1875 Mar 3
    - Booth congratulates Bowles on the result of the Phelps libel suit. He speaks again of Pacheco for governor of California., 1875 May 28
    - Booth discusses the California Gubernatorial race of 1875 in the light of Miller, Pacheco, and Gorham., 1875 Jun 12
    - Booth discusses thepossibilityin 1875 as to whether the Republican vote will dominate., 1875 Aug 8
    - Booth has read his official nomination for senator., 1875 Oct 8
    - Booth does not think that the stability of the British Consulcan be questioned., 1875 Dec 9
    - Booth laments a certain amount of inconsistency in the Republican. He states he that he has not seen people whom he likes since Bowles' departure., 1875 Dec 19
    - Booth discusses the French as being theoretical and the Anglo Saxon as being perfect. Lot M. Morrill made a speech in which Booth says he doesn't know that domestic debts and credits of a company must be equal., 1876 Jan 8
    - Booth speaks of a near scene in the Senate. A speech was made by Boutwell which Booth believed to be an attempt to be as offensive as possible. The speech was bidding against Blaine and the slavery question., 1876 Mar 20
    - Newton Booth discusses the congressionalsituation in the U.S. in 1876 with Bowles., 1876 Apr 3
    - Booth thinks that Bowles will like Richard James Oglesby more now, since he knows him. Booth feels that Blaine of Maine is losing his popularity., 1876 Apr 21
    - Newton Booth tells Bowles that Grant is one who takes a superficial view of Lincoln's character., 1876 May 9
    - Booth wonders where the U.S. would have been today without John Brown. Booth believes a need exists for John Brown today. He indicates that no one is sincere., 1876 May 16
    - Booth corrects an article in the Republican that says that an amendment first made by his was afterwards defeated. His defeat was on the amendment of the second section. Booth says that this put him in a false position with Dawes, and Dawes made unkind remarks in a speech., 1877 Feb 18
    - Booth speaks of a meeting of the Republican and the T. H., 1877 Aug 12
    - Booth informs Bowles that he has scarcely a hope of carrying the legislature, especially since Aaron Augustus Sargent is a candidate., 1877 Aug 28
  - Bowles discusses in this unascribed letter the position of the Phelps suit against the Republican [copy], 1856
    - Bowles grants Blaine's request of affairs in the Republican. Bowles states that he believes Blaine's "taste and modes of political advancement" are quite different than the fastidious ones of the Republican and Mr. Dawes. Bowles tells Blaine that he has sinned against his own personal self., 1869 Mar 23
    - Bowles points out that Blaine's letter of March 24 was "inexcusable, ill-tempered, and insulting." Bowles said that their personal relationship was now cut off and that he would make the most of Blaine's mistakes., 1869 Apr 6
    - Bowles states a few reasons why he considers Blaine's actions in the Speakership Contest as having shown impropriety: Blaine personally solicited votes and Blaine personally superintended the election., 1869 Apr 9
    - Bowles returns the letter of March 24 to Blaine and states that it is all that stands between personal friendship with Blaine; Bowles mentions the Speakership Contest againbutagrees to hold it in abeyance., 1869 Apr 13
    - Bowles tells J. C. Collins that he has read a letter and speech from him with interest. He says that he will be in Cincinnati as a journalist. Bowles feels that the reform needed in the country is to unite the best men of both parties., 1872 Mar 22